「炎刀·銃」
Entou Jyuu.
With this sword pair, the collection of the 12 Perfected Deviant Blades is now complete.
この一対の刀で
完成形変体刀十二本　その全てが揃ったというわけだ
Thank you for your hard work, Strategian Togame.
役目ご苦労だった　奇策士咎め
Emonzaemon!
右衛門左衛門
Regrettable.
取り合わず　これはあくまでも私の仕事
But I must do my duty.
Why?
何で　どうして
Why?!
Did I not already say?
いわなかったか
That woman is the daughter of the leader of the last rebellion, Hida Takahito.
その女は先の大乱の首謀者
飛騨鷹比等の一人娘
Princess Yousha...
容赦姫
Princess... Yousha?
容赦　姫
The fact that the Princess and the Strategian's battle had to end this way is entirely your fault, Kyotouryuu.
姫様と奇策士殿の対立の物語が
このような終結を迎えだのは
全てお前のせいだ　虚刀流
Entou
Jyuu
Gun,
the Flame
What do you think history is?
You naturally have the history that you know
Your own history
Your
own
history
For example...
Let’s say that history is nothing but words
There is no way to determine
if those words are the truth
Not a dark History, rather a false history
That history will also end with this chapter
Bind it, open it
Then close it
Togame! Togame!
咎め
Togame!
Now that it's come to this, I have no more reason to fight you.
今となっては　お前と戦う意味は何一つない
だから情けをかけてやった
That's why I showed some pity.
I avoided hitting her vitals.
急所ははずしてやる
She will die soon, but she's still alive for now.
もうすぐ死ぬが　まだ生きている
You have a chance to speak with her one last time.
末期の会話くらいは交わすがよかろう
そして聞いてやれ
And hear her, Strategian Togame...
奇策士咎め
No, Princess Yousha's final words.
いや
容赦姫の最後の言葉を
What will she say as she dies?
彼女が何と言って死ぬのか
咎め
Togame!
I can hear you...
聞えっておる
咎め
Togame!
I feel like my insides have been churned up.
内臓を引っかき回された気分だ
I get it now.
なるほどな　今のが「炎刀·銃」か
So that's Entou Jyuu...
I understand how it works now.
その仕組みは大体理解した
Who cares about what his sword does?!
どうでもいいよ
やつの刀の特性何て
Shichika...
七花
I'm sorry.
ごめん　俺はあんたの刀なのに　あんたを傷つけて
I'm supposed to be your sword, but I let you get hurt.
少し静かにしてくれるか
Be quiet for a bit.
今　とりあえず今後の策を練っておる
I'm thinking up a counter-strategy right now.
Well, it could be a scheme, depending on how it goes.
まあ　例によって奇策だがな
This is pretty rough, though.
しかし　さすがに無理か
Nothing comes to mind.
打つ手なしだ
Togame!
咎め
We lost.
私たちの負けだ
Well, even though I'm going to die, you'll still be alive,
まあ　私が死ぬだけで
そなたが死ななかったのだから
so it's not all bad.
よしとするか
な　何ゆってだよ
What are you talking about?
You can't die!
あんたが死ぬわけないだろう
I'll take you to a doctor!
すぐに医者を
It's pointless.
無理だ
I've already tried to think of some way out, but this is kind of hopeless.
いろいろ考えたが
ちょっとこれは　どうしようもない
Shichika...
七花
何だ
Yes?
私が死んだら
When I die, could you make sure
ちぇりおを
気合をいるための掛け声として
the whole country picks up "Cheerio" as a shout of encouragement in my place?
日本中に流行らせてくれ
Don't say that like you're giving up!
何弱気なことを
It seems this is it for me.
私はどうやら　ここまでのようだ
だから七花
That's why, Shichika...
"Cheerio" is my last wish.
どうか　ちえりおのことだけは頼む
ちえりおを間違って意味で流行らせるなんて
How can I spread the wrong meaning to "Cheerio" to the whole country by myself?!
そんなの俺一人じゃできないよ
You can do it.
そなたならできるさ
After all, you're the sword I chose.
そなたは私が選んだ刀だ
I can't!
無理だ　咎めが言ってくれなきゃ
Without you I can't do anything!
俺なんか何もできないよ
Don't say that.
何を言う
In this past year, I've taught you all I could.
この一年で　私はそなたに教えられる限りのことは教えた
You don't need to rely on my schemes anymore.
もう私の奇策などそなたには必要ないさ
しっかりしろうよ
Stay with me!
咎めにはまだやらなくちゃいけないことはあるだろう
There are still things you need to do!
Things I need to do?
やらなくではいけないことか
I walked this path alone for twenty years,
二十年 孤独にこの道を歩んできた私だが
but in this single year with you, you've taught me,
出会ってたかが一年のそなたに　私のほうこそ教えられた
exactly how a person should live.
人は　どう生きるべきなのかを
I haven't done anything to make you change your view of life that much!
いや
俺はまだそこまであんた人生観を変えるようなことはしてねえよう
You have.
してくれたさ
You've taught me so much.
数え切れないほどに何かを　してくれた
The things I've realized because of you,
そなたのお陰で気づいたこと
the things I've come to understand because of you,
そなたのお陰でわかったこと
the things I've discovered because of you...
そなたのお陰で見つけたこと
There are so many I've lost count.
数え切れなくて
もう　わけがわからぬ
I had fun because of you.
そなたのお陰で楽しかった
I was happy because of you.
そなたのお陰でうれしかった
I laughed, I smiled, I played because of you.
そなたのお陰で笑って　喜んで　はしゃいで
It was almost like I was a different person.
まるで　自分が自分でないようだった
Because of you, I...
そなたのお陰で私は　変れるのではないかとさえ思えた
I believed that even I could change.
咎め
Togame...
But, in the end, I...
だけど
結局　私は
couldn't change.
変れなかったのだ
This is a fitting way for me to die.
相応しい死に様であろう
The way someone like me should die.
私など　この程度だ
I was never qualified to hold you.
所詮　そなたを所有する資格などなかった
No one else could possibly hold me!
俺の所有者があんた以外にいるわけねえだろう
俺を腹心にしてくれるって言ったしゃねえか
Didn't you say I was your trusted partner?!
刀集め終わっても旅を続けて
After we finished, weren't we going to keep traveling together and make a map of the country?!
一緒に地図を作るんじゃなかったのかよ
You have me with you, and I have you, right?!
あんたには俺がいるし　俺にはあんたがいるんじゃなかったのかよ
Are you saying that was all a lie?!
あれは全部
嘘だったのか
It was all a lie.
全部　嘘だった
When the sword collection journey finished, I was going to kill you.
刀集めの旅が終われば
私は　そなたを殺すつもりであったよ
Just like everyone before you.
今までと　同じように
No way...
そんなこと
Everything was just a tool for my schemes.
何もかもが
所詮私にとっては　奇策のための道具だってに過ぎる
私の心さえ
Even my own heart.
It's just a pawn on the board.
ただの駒に過ぎぬのだ
Heart
Feelings
Emotions
They’re
nothing but tools I can use.
私はそういう人間だ
That's the kind of person I am.
I can only live by calculation.
私は計算ずくでしか生きられない
The part of me that trusted you was just another pawn to me.
そなたを信頼した　私という存在も
私にとっては　駒に過ぎぬ
Kyotouryuu took my father's head in front of my own eyes.
私の目の前で　父の首が刎ねた虚刀流
How could I possibly forgive that?
許せるわけがなかろうか
Even so...
だけと
Even so, I thought I could forgive you for that.
だけと　そなただから許そうと思った
But even that feeling was just a pawn, too.
そんな気持ちも　私にとってはただの駒だ
Even the thought that you might not just be another pawn, was itself another pawn on my board.
そなたを駒でないと思ったそんな気持ちも
私にとっては　ただの駒なのだ
If that's the truth, then what are feelings to you?!
だったら　あんたにとって感情って一体何なんだよ
俺が得た　俺がこの一年で得た喜怒哀楽って
The emotions that I gained in this last year,
一体何なんだよ
what are they?!
What is this that you taught me, that I feel in my heart?!
あんたから教えられたこの感情は　一体何なんだ
A pawn.
駒だ
Joy, anger, sorrow, fun...
喜びも怒りも悲しみも楽しみも　すべで私の駒だ
They were all pawns to me.
Insignificant objects that I need not control.
制御する必要のない　取るに足りない代物だ
But why did you have to tell all those lies?!
それなら
そうだとしたらどうしてそんな嘘付く必要があったんだよ
俺はあんたが死ぬと言ったら
I'd have killed myself for you if you just said the word!
いつでも死ぬのに
Even if the words were lies,
言葉は嘘でも
the feelings weren't.
気持ちは　嘘ではない
I simply thought it best to say that at the moment.
そんな風に思っていることを
あそこで言うのが一番いいと そう考えただけだ
Though I know it makes no difference.
それが叶わぬことだと知っていっても
But in the end, you're the one who got hurt the most!
結局　一番傷付いてるのはあんたじゃないか
I know.
そうだよ
そうでなければ　奇策など練られない
If that weren't the case, I wouldn't scheme.
Then what was the point to your life?
だったら　あんたの人生って一体何のためにあったんだよ
You had the right to be happy!
あんたにだって幸せになる権利はあっただろうが
And yet you kept hurting yourself and hurting yourself and hurting yourself,
それなのに傷ついて傷ついて傷ついて
and here in the end, you're lying in the middle of the road, dying.
最後にはこんな道半ばで撃たれて死んで
What the hell were you doing?!
あんた一体何やってんだよ
Are you stupid?!
馬鹿じゃないのか
You're absolutely right.
まったく　その通りだ
でもな
But...
Right now,
わたしは今　とても幸せだよ
I'm very happy.
Even dying in the middle of a road, I'm happy.
道半ばで撃たれて死んで　幸せだ
Because this way, I don't have to kill you.
これで　そなたを殺さずに済んだのだから
Togame...
とがめ
Finally...
やっと　やっとこれで全部やめることができる
Now I can finally lay down all my burdens.
死ななきゃ止まれなかったのか
Couldn't you have done that without dying?!
Did you have to keep going, until it came down to this?!
こんなことになるまで　あんたは止まれなかったのか
It wasn't your fault.
そなたのせいではないよ
とがめ
Togame...
7th generation head of Kyotouryuu,
虚刀流七代目当主
Yasuri Shichika.
鑢七花
This is my final order.
最後の命令だ
Forget all about me and everything that's happened with me, and live on as you wish.
わたしのことは忘れて
これまでの何もかもを忘れて
好きなように生きろ
The contract I made with you ends with my death.
そなたとの契約は
わたしの死をもって終了とする
You can stop falling for me now.
そなたはもう　わたしに惚れずとも良い
Like hell!
ふざけんなよ
あんたといることが　おれの好きなことだったのに
I loved being with you!
おれはあんたが　本当に好きだったのに
I...
I really loved you!
Shichika...
七花
What am I supposed to do now?
これからどうすればいいんだよ
I can't do anything without you!
あんたがいなきゃ　おれは何にもできないよ
You really are cute.
本当に　可愛い奴だ
Hey, Shichika...
なあ　七花
I'm selfish and egocentric...
わたしは自分勝手で　自己中心的で
I'm an idiot who could only think of revenge,
復讐のこと以外は　何も考えることができず
with my stupidity cured only by death.
死ななければ治らないような馬鹿で
A terrible woman who treated you as nothing but a tool,
そなたを散々道具扱いした
酷い　何の救いもないような　死んで当然の女だけれど
whose only fate is death.
Even so...
それでも　わたしは
Would you mind...
そなたに惚れてもよいか
if I fell for you?
Well met.
よくぞ参った　面をあげよ
Owari Castle
Raise your head.
恐悦至極にございます
It is my deepest honor.
I am the 8th Shogun of the Owari Shogunate, Yanari Masatsuna.
余が尾張幕府八代将軍　家鳴匡綱じゃ
At last, an audience.
ついにお目通りがかなった
That woman also had such a wish.
これは　あの女の望みでもあったこと
I win.
わたしは勝ったのだ
Let me hear what you have to say then.
では　そのほうが言う大事とやらの話を聞こうではないか
First, your Lordship...
しかし　大御所さま
I believe I asked for a private audience?
お人払いをお願いしたはずですが
Worry not.
安心せい　こやつらは代々将軍に仕えてきた者どもじゃ
They have worked under the Shogun for generations.
Their loyalty to me is absolute.
繋がりは絶対であり　裏切るようなことはありえん
They would never betray me.
You could say they are part of my own body.
言うなれば余と一心同体じゃ
左様でございますか
Is that so...
Part of his own body?
一心同体
Quite a statement to just throw out like that.
随分な言葉を平気で使う
It would seem that the 8th generation successor by inheritance is of this low caliber.
もらったものを受け継いだだけの八代目など
この程度か
You are the swordsmith Shikizaki Kiki's descendant, correct?
そのほうがかの刀鍛冶
四季崎記紀とやらの末裔であるというのは確かなことなんじゃな
はい
Yes.
Do you have evidence?
何か証でもあるのか
物事を判断する際
It is foolish to rely on simply on physical evidence when making a decision.
そのようなものに頼るのは愚か者のやり方です
Quite right.
ぬかしおる　ならば申せ
Speak, then.
Yes.
はい
To begin with, the man named Shikizaki Kiki was not a swordsmith.
そもそも　四季崎記紀という男は　刀鍛冶ではございません
I won't say they had a good lineage,
何千年も前から続く由緒正しき
but he was of a family of soothsayers with a history of several thousand years.
とは言えないにせよ 歴史ある占術師の家系です
His objective was the falsification of history.
彼の目的は歴史の改竄にありました
Falsifying history?
歴史の改竄
そのための完成形変体刀でした
It was for that purpose that the Perfected Deviant Blades were forged.
I don't understand.
わからんの　何故そのような真似を目論むしようがある
Why would he wish
to do something like alter history?
ええ　それが肝要ですね
That is indeed an important point.
Well, at heart, he did it for the sake of Japan.
まあ　強いて言うなら
日本というこの国のためでしょうか
Has your Lordship ever turned your attention to other countries?
大御所さまは　海の外に目を向けたことはございますか
About a hundred years from now,
今からおよそ百年後くらいでしょうか
this country will suffer an attack from foreign nations, and then perish.
この国は諸外国から一斉に攻撃を受けて　滅びます
Perish?
滅ぶ
This was predicted by the founder of the family several thousand years ago.
それが数千年前　一族初代が残した予言にございます
Princess.
姫さま
Silence.
お静かに
You're late, idiot.
遅いのよ　この愚か者
What is it?
それでどうかしたの
An invader entered this castle just moments ago.
つい先頃　この尾張城に侵入者がありました
And why are you telling me this?
それをどうしてわたしに報告するの
I'm in the middle of a very important conversation.
今わたしはとても大事な話をしているのだけれど
It would appear that the intruder is none other than that man.
その侵入者というのが　どうやらあの男のようです
ええ　うん　なるほど
I see.
これも四季崎記紀の思惑通りなのかしら
I wonder if this is also as Shikizaki Kiki planned?
That man, huh...
彼がね
Hey, just what are you getting at?
おいそのほう　何を言っておる
わけのわからん侵入者など 大事無いわ
Such a worthless intruder is of no importance.
No, your Lordship.
いえ　大御所様
This is the end for us both.
我々はこれで　おしまいです
Togame...
とがめ
It doesn't look like I can follow your order.
おれはもうあんたの命令を守れそうにないや
Why can't they stop him?!
何故止められぬ
He is but a sole intruder!
賊はたったの一人なのであろうが
Do not underestimate him.
侮ってはいけません
After all, he is the warrior who assembled eleven of the swords.
何せ彼は実質上一人で変体刀を十一本まで集めてみせた精鋭なのですから
W-What?!
あ　なに
He is the 7th generation head of Kyotouryuu, Yasuri Shichika.
虚刀流七代目当主　鑢七花
Kyotouryuu...
虚刀流
I see!
そうか
The swordsman who uses no sword I read about in the report!
報告にあった刀打つ変る剣法
But there are over a thousand soldiers in Owari Castle!
しかし　この尾張城内は千人以上の兵士がいるんじゃぞ
Unfortunately, no number of soldiers will be able to stop him.
残念ながら　こちらが何万人いようと　何の関係もないでしょう
You talk too much, Emonzaemon.
口が過ぎるわよ　右衛門左衛門
But he is right.
でもその通りね
Why?!
何故じゃ　何故余の城を襲う
Why is Kyotouryuu attacking my castle?!
虚刀流はそのほうの部下ではなかったのか
Is he not your subordinate?!
わたしの部下と言えるのは
The only one I call my subordinate is Souda Emonzaemon here.
この世には左右田右衛門左衛門ひとりですよ
In fact, Yasuri Shichika is under direct control of the strategian.
鑢七花は奇策士の直轄ですからね
Then summon the strategian here at once!
ならばその奇策士を呼べ
Have her command Kyotouryuu to stop!
虚刀流を止めるように命令するのじゃ
Unfortunately, she died while collecting the swords.
生憎　彼女は刀集めの途中で　落命しましたゆえ
Oh, did I not mention that?
あれ　言ってませんでしたっけ
Well, it would appear that her servant has gone berserk upon losing his master.
まああるじを失った従僕が乱心した　という運びのようですね
しかし大御所様　これはわたし達にとって最悪ではありながら
But your Lordship, this may be both a blessing and a curse at the same time.
同時に幸運かもしれません
H-How?
ど　どうして
彼こそが四季崎記紀の目論見を
He is a part of Shikizaki Kiki's plan, the final piece necessary to ensure the success of our goal.
わたし達の悲願を達成するための最後の鍵だからです
In other words, the Completed Deviant Blade.
つまり完了形変体刀の
完了形
Completed?
ここに至ることこそが
It would seem that Shikizaki Kiki's plan included this.
どうやら四季崎記紀の目論見であったようですね
Please look on this as the ceremony that heralds
これは家鳴将軍家の天下を盤石のものとし
a thousand years of prosperity for the Yanari Shogunate.
千年の繁栄を約束するための儀式であるとお考えください
つまり　乱心した虚刀流を返り討ちにすればよいのじゃな
So you're saying that we just need stop Kyotouryuu's killing spree?
I don't get your reasoning, though...
理屈はよくわからぬが
Indeed.
しかし少しばかり面倒で　厄介な手順を踏む必要がございます
There is a bit of a tedious process that we must follow though.
なるほど　わたしにとって好ましくなかった「彼ら」は
I see.
I don't like them, but they will be used here, like this.
ここでこういう風に使うわけか
Using the eleven whom your Lordship calls part of your own body,
大御所さまと一心同体だというこの場の十一人
along with my trusted Souda Emonzaemon, making twelve.
それに　わたしの腹心である左右田右衛門左衛門を合わせた十二人で
Let us go put the finishing touches on this history.
この歴史の最後の仕上げを行なうと致しましょう
Kyotouryuu.
虚刀流
虚刀流よくぞ来た　と言ってやりたいが
I'd like to welcome you at this point...
but I am at a loss for words.
わたしとしては理解できないところだ
折角見逃してやった命だというのに
To think you'd endanger that life which I went out of my way to spare...
それをあたら粗末にするとは
右衛門左衛門
Emonzaemon?
Aioi Ninpou: Ventriloquism.
相生忍法·声帯移し
Well, that's not really important.
まあ　そんなことはどうでもよい
虚刀流よ　既に一般兵は退かせた
Kyotouryuu.
I have ordered the soldiers' retreat.
それ以上無駄な戦いを続ける必要はない
There is no more need for pointless fights.
逃げ回る必要もない
Nor is there any need for you to run around wildly.
一直線に天守閣へ向かえ
Head straight for the castle keep.
わたしも姫さまも　そこで待っている
The Princess and I await you there.
待っているだと
Waiting for me?
You've come to avenge the strategian, correct?
奇策士殿の仇を討ちに来たのだろう
I believe that you will be able to break through.
お前なら突破できると信じているぞ
違うよ
You're wrong.
おれはとがめの仇を討ちに来たんじゃない
I didn't come here to avenge Togame.
死にに来たんだ
I came here to die.
ああ　面倒だ
What a hassle...
7th generation head of Kyotouryuu, Yasuri Shichika.
虚刀流七代目当主　鑢七花
We are the eleven retainers to the Yanari Shogunate!
我ら家鳴将軍家十一人衆が
お待っていたぞ
We shall be your opponents!
家鳴将軍家御側人十一人衆がひとり　般若丸
I am one of the eleven retainers to the Yanari Shogunate, Hannyamaru!
Hannyamaru
Zettou Kanna
I know, Kyotouryuu.
知ってるんだぜ　虚刀流
お前はこの絶刀だけは折ることも曲げることも適わないんだよなあ
You are unable to bend or break this sword!
Your luck ran out when I became your first opponent.
俺が最初乗ったことが運のつきで
報復絶刀
Houfuku Zettou!
もう手加減の必要は無くなったからなあ
I don't have to hold back anymore.
Zettou Kanna
Broken
一本目
First sword.
Oniyadori Furachi
Zantou Namakura
そう　俺は結局そいつの刀身を目にしなかったんだ
Oh yeah, I never did see through his strike.
And you will never see anything again!
そして　二度と目にすることはない
これは　虚刀流のわざとしては名前がない
This Kyotouryuu move has no name.
それほどに当たり前の技術だ
It's that simple of a move.
In other words, that's just how mediocre your attack is.
つまり　あんたの居合いはそれほどに取るに足らないことだ
Zantou
Namakura
Broken
Second sword.
二本目
私は千刀巡りを付け焼刃ではない　完全なものとして使える
I didn't just learn Sentou Meguri, I have mastered it.
Tomoe
Akatsuki
Sentou
Tsurugi
So what?
それがどうした
I hesitated against Meisai because I couldn't come to terms with her personality.
俺が迷彩のことが苦手だったのは
あいつの性格が苦手だったからだよ
Sentou
Tsurugi
Broken
Third sword.
三本目
Fugi Matsuaki
Hakutou Hari
After killing the man who killed Sabi, I will for the first time surpass him.
錆を倒したお前を倒すことで
初めて　僕は錆を超えられるのさ
白兎開眼
Hakutou Kaigan!
完全の軌跡を描いて振らなければ砕けてしまうほどで脆い刀
If you don't swing in a perfect arc, that sword is so frail it shatters.
そいつはこっちの体の筋をずらせば　それだけで攻撃を防げるんだよ
All I have to do is shift a little, and I can stop your attack.
When I fought Sabi, I wasn't allowed to break the sword, so my options were limited.
錆と戦う時は
刀を壊すわけにはいかなかったから使えないてたんだな
Hakutou Hari
Broken
Fourth sword.
四本目
Iga Kairo
Zokutou Yoroi
I won't be careless even with this armor's perfect defense!
俺は　鎧の防御力を頼って油断したりしねえ
I'll run you through before capturing you!
捕まる前に　お前の肉体をぶっ貫いてやるぜ
Yoroi transfers any outside shock away from the user by being in contact with the ground.
鎧ってのは地面と接していることで
衝撃を外へ逃がしてんだってなあ
地面や壁と接していない空中なら
If I hit you midair where you aren't touching the ground or walls, the shock can't go anywhere.
食らった衝撃はどこにも逃げられない
Zokutou Yoroi   Broken
Fifth sword.
五本目
I am of the lineage of the Maniwa Corps.
僕は　出自を辿れば真庭忍軍の者でしたね
Maniwa Boufura
Soutou Kanazuchi
双刀の犬
Soutou Noinu!
忍法を使って重さを消してるんだろうけど
You're using ninpou to negate its weight,
重さが無くなったこの刀に何の意味があるんだよ
but if you take that away, what's the point to this sword?
Crap!
しまった
あんたより弱い真庭には
You're probably the weakest Maniwani I've met.
さすがにいなかったよ
Soutou
Kanazuchi
Broken
Sixth sword.
六本目
俺のような健康優良な戦士が使うのとでは
When a warrior with such perfect health as I use it, Akutou Bita becomes something else entirely.
同じ悪刀七味であろうと　その実体はまるで違う意味合いだ
俺は真に不死身の戦士だ
I am a truly immortal warrior.
Uron
Akutou
Bita
Just because you don't die if I kill you,
殺して死なないからといって
it doesn't mean you can't die if I keep killing you.
殺し続けて死なないわけじゃないだろう
雛罌粟から沈丁花まで　打撃技混成接続
From Red Poppy to Daphne, a mixed-connection fist strike.
You've died 272 times.
あんたは　二百七十二回死んだよ
Akutou
Bita
Broken
七本目
Seventh sword.
Haiga Ou
Bitou
Kanzashi
人形殺法　微風東風
Doll Fatality: Zephyr Swordstorm!
七花八裂　応用編
Shichika Hachiretsu: Revamp
Shichika Hachiretsu
Revamp
二対一だぞ
It was two against one...
日和号を一台相手にしたときでさえ
I thought you had trouble fighting against Biyorigou alone.
あんたは相当に苦戦したはずなのに
You were in the way, so Biyorigou couldn't show its full strength.
あんたが邪魔で　日和号は実力を発揮できなかったんだ
Bitou
Kanzashi
Broken
八本目
Eighth sword.
I cannot imagine there is any meaning to a fight like this.
このような戦いに意味があるとは思えない
Sumigaoka Kokubo
Outou Nokogiri
王刀楽土というのだろう
Outo Rakudou, I believe it's called?
この刀を手にしたとたん
The instant I took up this sword, I felt a cruel calmness.
ひどく穏やかな気持ちに
尾張一の獰猛者として知られたこの私が
To the point where I thought I could just let you go, as the most honorable of the Owari.
お前を見逃してやってもよいと思うほどになる
どうだ
What say you?
そうか　ならばせめて一撃で殺してやる
I see.
Then I shall grant you death in one blow.
Your words are nothing but talk that will never sway me.
あんたの言葉　上っ面ばかりで全然心打たねえ
Outou
Nokogiri
Broken
Ninth sword.
九本目
This thing is kind of useless...
さすがにこれ　どうしようもないんですけど
Saraba Kousha
Seitou Hakari
とりあえず投げて使えば
Why don't you try throwing it at me?
ほかに方法もなさそうなので
It doesn't look like there's any other way, so I suppose I'll do that.
そうさせてもらいます
Seitou
Hakari
Broken
Tenth sword.
十本目
Rogiri Bangai
Dokutou Mekki
Rogiri, Rogiri!
呂桐　呂桐　四季崎四季崎四季崎四季崎
Shikizaki, Shikizaki, Shikizaki, Shikizaki!
今　解放してやるからな
I will free you now.
Dokutou
Mekki
Broken
十一本目
Eleventh sword.
This is seriously a hassle.
本当に面倒だ
That was fast, Shichika-kun.
早かったわね　七花君
Souda Emonzaemon   Entou Jyuu
I suppose this is the true strength of Kyotouryuu, now that you're allowed to destroy the swords.
これこそが刀の破壊を許された虚刀流の
真の力ということなのかしら
天守閣で待ってるって言わなかったか
Didn't you say you'd be waiting in the castle keep?
否定するわ
I deny that.
君はここで死んじゃうかもしれないからさ
You might die here, after all.
最後に顔を見ておこうかと思ってね
I thought I'd take a look at your face one more time.
ああ ちなみに奇策士のことは大嫌いだったけど
Incidentally, I hated that strategian, but I hold no animosity towards you.
君の事は別に嫌いじゃなかったわよ
まっ　右衛門左衛門を倒すことができたら
Well, if you do manage to defeat Emonzaemon, come up these stairs.
この階段を上がってきなさい
そこまでこれたら私を　殺させてあげる
If you make it that far,
I'll let you kill me.
Princess...
お姫様　あのさ
I'm—
Emonzaemon!
右衛門左衛門　命令してあげる
This is an order.
殺しなさい
Kill him.
仰せのままに
As you wish.
ただ　私が虚刀流を殺してしまうと
But if I kill Kyotouryuu, Shikizaki Kiki's plan will never come to fruition.
四季崎の目論見は達成できないままに終わるということになりますが
That's true.
そうね
However, you may not have realized it yet,
だけどひょっとしたらあんたはまだ気づいていないかもしれないけど
私ってとても否定的な人間なのよ
but I'm a very denying kind of person.
I want to see Shikizaki Kiki's plans destroyed just as much as I want to see them completed.
四季崎の悲願を達成したいのと同じぐらいに
その悲願が挫けるところも見てみたいのよ
あんたならそのどちらかを必ず見せてくれると信じているわ
I trust that you'll show me one way or the other!
Unpleasant.
面白からず
まさかこんな形でお前と対することになろうとは思わなかった
I didn't think I'd be facing you like this.
What do you mean?
どういう意味だよ
I mean, manipulated like a puppet in someone's palm.
何者かの手のひらの上で踊らされるように
という意味だ
私は戦う時は姫様の意志だけで戦いたい
I wish to fight only for the Princess' sake.
四季崎の思惑のままに戦うなど
The thought of fighting for the sake of Shikizaki Kiki is extremely unpleasant.
不愉快至極　極まりない
だから　どっかずれてんだよなあ　あんたたちって
Like I said, you're all wrong.
Maybe in the end, it really is pointless to fight for someone.
やっぱりさ　誰かのために何かをするなんてこと
人間には　刀にも無理なんじゃないかって
For both humans and swords.
I came to believe that after Togame died.
咎めが死んだことで　俺はそう思ったよ
At the start, I obeyed Togame without any resolution at all,
最初は覚悟もなく咎めに従って
and after a while I obeyed her for her sake after finding resolve.
途中からは覚悟を持って　咎めに従ってきたけどさ
What do you fight for?
If you have to think about it, then you shouldn't be fighting in the first place.
そんなことを考えなければならないぐらいなら
そもそも戦わなければいい
だってさ
After all, in the end, Togame was only thinking about herself.
結局のところ咎めは自分のことしか考えてなかったんだぜ
最後の最後まで自分勝手にさ
She kept telling me to live how I liked until her last breath.
俺に好きに生きろうとか言ってさ
She really was selfish.
本当にわがままでさ
I wonder what you call people like her...
何って言うんだろうなあ　ああいうのは
But I can't help it.
でも仕方ねえんだよ
俺は　そういう咎めのことが好きになったんだから
I fell in love with Togame because of that.
虚刀流七代目当主 鑢七花
I am the 7th generation head of Kyotouryuu,
Yasuri Shichika.
いざ尋常に
Let the match...
始め
Begin!
I loved that part of her!
咎めのそういうところが好きだったんだから
俺もまた 俺のためにだけ戦ってたんだと思うぜ
That's why I think now that I was only fighting for myself.
Then what are you invading this castle for?
なら
お前は
何のために乗り込んできたのだ
To die.
死ぬためだ
とがめは 俺に生きろと言ったけど
Togame told me to live,
俺はもう そんな命令に従う必要は ないから
but I don't have any duty to obey that order anymore.
I don't think anyone but you can kill me.
俺を殺せるのはあんたをおいてほかにいないと考えてるぜ
とがめを殺した あんたしか
You, the one who killed Togame...
笑わず
Unhumorous.
これが 四季崎のもくろみどおりなのだとすれば
If this really is part of Shikizaki Kiki's plan, then it really is comical.
確かにこっけいなものだ
動く的には当てられないという考えか
Do you think that your movements make you harder to hit?
If you have come here to die then it is unavoidable.
死にに来たというなら是非もない
Die, with your regrets!
悔いを残して死ね
What will you say as you die?
お前は何と言って死ぬのかな
バカな
I-Impossible!
あれだけの弾を どうやってかわしたというのだ
How did you dodge so many bullets?
かわしてないよ
I didn't dodge them.
最初から食らうつもりで 覚悟を決めたからな
I resolved to take them from the start.
虚刀流
Kyotouryuu...
Togame gave me an order...
俺は とがめに命令されていた
俺自身を守れと
To protect myself.
But I no longer have a duty to obey that order.
だが その命令を守る必要は もうどこにもない
Are you trying to die?
お前 死ぬ気か
I already said so.
そう言ったろうが
He's allowed to break the swords.
刀の破壊を許された　そして
And...
he's allowed to hurt himself.
自ら傷つくことを許された
鑢七花の
This is Yasuri Shichika's true power.
これが本当の 実力
不忍法·不生不殺
Shinobazuhou Ikasazukorosazu...
いや 断罪炎刀
No,
Danzai Entou!
虚刀流奥義
Kyoutouryuu Ultimate Move!
Shichika Hachiretsu!
七花八裂
Kai!
改
Completed Deviant Blade
Kyotou Yasuri
Entou
Jyuu
Broken
P-Princess...
What on earth is happening down there?
状況はいったい どうなっておるのじゃ
Everything is going favorably.
事は全て順調に進んでおります
It won't be long before our wish will be granted.
わたしたちの悲願は 程なく達成されそうですよ
I-I see.
そっ そうか
That's good then.
これで よいのじゃな
So the Yanari Shogunate will be granted a thousand years of prosperity now, right?
これで 家鳴家の天下は1000年の繁栄を約束されるのじゃな
Yes.
Emonzaemon's dying words.
右衛門左衛門の 散り際の一言だ
Steel your heart and listen.
心して聞け
I'm listening.
聞くわよ なあに
What were they?
"Princess, please forgive me for dying for your sake."
「姫さま　あなたのために死ぬことを お許しください」
最期までしんきくさいやつよね
An annoying man right to the end.
Was he trying to impress me with a line like that?
そんなこと言ってわたしが感動するとでも思っているのかしら
Well, whatever.
まあいいわ それじゃさっさと終わりにしましょうか
How about we finish this then?
Shichika-kun, as promised, you may kill me.
七花君 約束どおりわたしを 殺してもいいわよ
W-Wait!
まっ 待て
What are you saying?!
何を言っておる
Someone... Someone help!
誰か 誰かおらぬか
残念ながら あと１人くらいしか相手を できそうにない
Unfortunately, I don't think I can take on more than one more person.
P-Princess Hitei!
ひっ 否定姫 何をぼけっと見ておるのだ
Stop sitting there and save me!
Please, don't be silly.
いやあ無茶を言わないでくださいよ
I don't have the slightest bit of combat ability.
わたしには戦闘力はありませんし
And if you don't die, this won't end.
それに あなたが殺されなきゃ話が終わらないじゃないですか
W-What did you say?!
なっ 何だと
家鳴将軍家1000年の繁栄というのは嘘です
All that about the Yanari Shogunate lasting a thousand years was a lie.
It was just a means to speak with you.
あなたに人払いをさせるための方便でした
貴様
Why, you!
だって尾張幕府の崩壊こそが四季崎記紀の目論見だったんですから
After all, the collapse of the Owari Shogunate was Shikizaki Kiki's objective.
正確には 某幕府の某将軍家体制のはずだったんですけどね
Well, it was originally supposed to be a different Shogunate and Shogun's household,
そっちの成立は阻止できたものの
but after preventing them from coming to power,
your family took over the country in a similar manner and built up peace across the country.
代わりに似たようなあなたが
天下をとって同じように天下太平を築いちゃったんじゃ同じことですから
歴史の修正作用ですか
Perhaps it was history self-correcting itself?
なっ 何を言っておる
W-What are you talking about?
It was a future which could have been.
あり得たかもしれない未来の話ですよ
Well, not future, but the original.
未来というより本来ですか
So that's what should have been?
では その方は最初から
My wish was to kill you.
わたしの目的はあなたを殺すことです
それが今やっと
And now...
成就されようとしています
that will finally be fulfilled.
Togame wasted her whole life because of you.
とがめはあんたみたいなやつのせいで人生を 棒に振っちまった
自業自得といえば それまでだが
Well, I suppose you could say she reaped what she sowed.
いまさらあんたを殺したからって
Killing you at this point wouldn't do anything to lift any burden off her.
とがめの無念が晴れるわけでも
Nor would I feel any better by doing it.
まして俺の気が晴れるわけでもないんだけどな
じゃったら
Then—
But, you see...
けどさ 示しはつけなきゃなんねえよな
I have to make an example of you.
Hey, Princess.
おい お姫さま
とがめから あんたに会ったら礼を言っておくように言われてたんだけど
Togame told me to thank you if I managed to run into you.
Oh?
I don't recall doing anything she'd thank me for though.
別にお礼を言われるようなことはしていないけど
Can I ask one thing?
１つだけ 聞いていいか
何なりと
Ask away.
あんた ホントはとがめのこと好きだったんじゃねえの
Deep down, you liked Togame, didn't you?
That unpleasant woman?
あの不愉快な女ね
I guess I didn't... dislike her.
嫌いじゃなく
なくもなかったわ
そっか
I see.
W-Wait!
まっ 待て
Calm down!
落ち着け
Listen to me!
余の話を聞け
Spare me!
いっ 命だけは
命だけは 助けてくれ
Please spare me!
そっそうじゃ その方に天下をやろう
Oh, I know!
I'll give you the country!
その方 天下が欲しくはないか
Don't you want power over the country?!
Like I'd give a damn about that!
いるかそんなもん
ちぇりおー
Cheerio!
nozomi wa yami no naka
My dreams, buried in the dark
umete nao omoidasu yo
Suddenly, they come to mind
You and I, when was it?
kimi ga watashi ga tooi hi ni
deatta natsukashisa
We met, far ago and long away
We travelled the road before us,
tabiji wa me no mae no
Chasing an unending dream,
owari naki yume wo
Reaching in the end
oikakete mata hitotsu
Another time to part
wakare wo te ni shite
adokenai kotoba
Innocent words,
kaze ni toketeita
Fading in the wind
Let us set upon the road again
mata suu ni nabirete wo
tsugi wa doko darou?
Where shall it take us next?
Japan really is big.
やっぱ広いなあ 日本は
Ah, there you are!
七花君 めっけ
Found you, Shichika-kun!
ついてきてくれと頼んだ覚えはないぞ
I don't remember asking you to follow me.
I'm not such a heartless person as to make you ask me to come along.
わたしは頼まれなきゃ動かないような冷血な人間じゃないからね
But I do remember asking you not to follow me.
ついてくるなと頼んだ覚えならある
Perhaps unfortunately, or perhaps fortunately,
残念ながらなのか 幸運ながらなのか
歴史の改ざんは行われませんでした
history was not falsified in the end.
単に匡綱の直系の息子が 九代将軍を襲名しただけでした
The son of one of Masatsuna's direct descendants simply succeeded the seat of the 9th shogun.
Shikizaki Kiki's descendant's attempts for a revolution in history,
四季崎 記紀の末裔が行おうとした
歴史に対する革命は
attempts to reform the world in history,
歴史に対する世直しは
and attempts to destroy history.
そして 歴史に対する破壊活動は
In one word, they ended in failure.
つまるところ 失敗に終わったのです
四季崎記紀は結局 負けちゃったのよ
Shikizaki Kiki lost in the end.
Everything started going off plan starting with Kyuu Shogun,
計算違いは旧将軍から始まった
そして飛騨鷹比等 そしてその娘
and then Hida Takahito,
and then his daughter.
It all ended with Princess Yousha.
容赦姫が決定的だったわね
If you ask me, all that stuff about altering history is like some fantasy tale.
俺に言わせりゃ 歴史の改ざんなんてそれこそ夢物語だぜ
If it it's like you say, and another country will sail here to destroy Japan,
あんたの言うとおり
海の向こうから やって来る連中が この国を滅ぼそうとしても
we can just leave it to the warriors of that time to fight back.
そのときは そのときの連中が 覚悟を決めて戦えばいいだけの話さ
まっ 改ざんは失敗しても改変くらいは できただろうから
Well, the falsification failed, but maybe it can still be altered a bit.
I'm sure Japan in a hundred years won't let itself be ruined like that so easily.
100年後の連中もただ 滅ぼされはしないでしょうね
Let’s hope they've got some guts.
ちょっとは根性 出してもらいましょう
What are you going to do now, Shichika-kun?
七花君 これからどうするの
I've seen most of Noto, so I think I'll move onto Kaga.
能登は もうじゅうぶんに見たから
次は 加賀かな
Kaga's apparently a pretty rich area.
加賀はお金がいっぱいあるらしいわよ
Shouldn't we replenish our war funds before heading there?
ここらで そろそろ軍資金を補充しといた方がよくない
I'll leave that stuff to you.
そういう方面はあんたに任せるよ
I don't know why you're following me, but be useful at least.
何であれ一緒にいるんだから
ちょっとは役に立ってくれ
You're so harsh.
厳しいわね 誰に似たんだか
A lot like a certain someone.
その代わり追っ手が来たら 俺が戦ってやるよ
In return, if any bandits attack, I'll take care of them.
Oh?
あっそう じゃあそんときはよろしく
I'll leave that to you then.
Yeah.
However, by that point you might be torn into pieces.
ただしそのころにはあんたは八つ裂きになっているかもしれないけどな
Why?!
何で
After that, there was no more news of Yasuri Shichika.
その後 鑢七花の消息を知る者は誰もいません
He may have died on the roadside in the middle of his journey,
あるいは旅の途上で 野垂れ死んだかもしれないし
or he may have completed the map of Japan, then sailed to a foreign country and continued his journey.
見事日本地図を完成させて
その後海の外へと 旅の行く先を定めたかもしれません
But even after everything was over,
しかし彼は 事が終わった後にも
after the historical plan connecting man and swords failed,
人と刀にまつわる歴史的なたくらみが失敗に終わった後にも
be it for a long or a short period, he certainly lived.
短期間であれ長期間であれ 確かに生きていました
That was something surely everyone wanted.
それはきっと 誰もが望んでいたことでした
The ones who failed at revenge...
復讐を果たせなかった者
The ones who failed at their goals...
目的を果たせなかった者
The ones who fell before achieving their aspirations...
志半ばで倒れた者
The ones who didn't succeed...
思いを遂げられなかった者
The ones who lost...
負けた者 くじけた者 朽ちた者
The ones who stumbled...
The ones who rotted...
一生懸命頑張って
The ones who fought with all their might, sacrificed everything,
ほかのあらゆる全てを犠牲にしてまで踏ん張って
just to have their work be for naught, yielding fruitless results,
それでも 行為がまったく結果につながらず
努力はまったく実を結ばず
who died unfairly, or perhaps illogically, tragically, without face, full of regrets...
理不尽に あるいは不合理に
ただただ無残に
ただただぶざまに
どうしようもなく後悔しながら死んでいった者たちの
The story which offers a happy future for them, filled with hopes and dreams...
夢と希望に満ちあふれた 未来を予感させる前向きな物語
"Katanagatari,"
『刀語』は
quietly lowers its curtains here.
ここで 静かに幕を下ろすのでございます